Guide to the Yale Political Union Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Yale Political Union records
1935-2004
RU 248
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
The records consist of correspondence, published materials, minutes, press releases, membership lists, memorabilia, and videotapes documenting the activities and operations of the Yale Political Union.
Yale University. Yale Political Union
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Political Union was founded in 1934 by A. Whitney Griswold, Max Millikan, and August Heckscher II. Its purpose is to stimulate interest and give training in public affairs. The Political Union is modeled somewhat after the Oxford University and Cambridge University unions, but is organized as a legislature under congressional rules, with floor leaders, honorary guest speakers, and voting on national issues.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, published materials, minutes, press releases, membership lists, memorabilia, and videotapes documenting the activities and operations of the Yale Political Union.
Related Materials Note
Party of the Right, Yale University, Records (RU 1101), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library).
College students -- Societies, etc.; Debates and debating; Political clubs; Videotapes; Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Yale Political Union
- Yale Political Union correspondence, 1946-1962; Accession 19ND-A-487
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - Correspondents
    - Acheson, Dean (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Allen, George V. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alpert, George (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anderson, Robert B. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Austin, Warren (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baldwin, Raymond (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baldwin, Roger N. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ball, George (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barden, Graham (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barkley, Alben W. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Beck, Thomas H. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Benn, Anthony Wedgewood (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Benson, Ezra Taft (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Berle, Adolphe (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bernard, Harold (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bevan, Aneurin (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bevis, Howard L. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bicks, Robert A. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biddle, Francis (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Block, Herbert L. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Blusztajn, Mieczyslaw (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Booher, Edward E. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boothby (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boren, Lyle H. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bowles, Chester (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bradley, J. Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brannan, Charles (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bredhoff, Elliot (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bricker, John W. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bridges, Styles (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - British Information Services (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Browder, Earl (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brownell, Herbert (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Budenz, Louis F. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bunche, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bush, Prescott (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Byrnes, James F. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Callejon, Don Eduardo Propper de (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Canhan, Erwin D. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cannon, Clarence (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Capehart, Homer (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Carey, James (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chang, John M. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chang, P. H. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chapman, Oscar L. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chingyu, Hu (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Clark, Tom C. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cole, W. Sterling (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Communist Party (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Conant, James B. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Connor, John T. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Conway, George (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cooper, John Sherman (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Costello, John A. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Coudert, Frederic (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cousins, Norman (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cretella, Albert (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cruikshank, Nelson (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cuban Embassy (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Culbertson, Ely (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Curley, James M. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dawson, Donald S. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dejany, Aouney W. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Democratic Party (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dewey, Thomas E. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - DeWitt, Nicholas (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Diggs, Charles C. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dilworth, Richardson (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dobbs, Farrell (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Donner, Frank J. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Douglas, Paul (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dubinsky, David (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Du Bridge, L. A. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Duff, James (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Duncan, Paul (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Eastland, James (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Eastman, Max (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Edwards, Alfred (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ernst, Morris (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ewing, Oscar R. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fast, Howard (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Flemming, Arthur S. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fong, Hiram L. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gaitskell, Hugh (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gallup, George (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Garrison, Lloyd K. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gavin, James (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gerson, Simon W. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gitlitz, Carl (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Graham, Frank (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Griffin, Robert P. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Griswold, A. Whitney (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hall, Gus (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hallinan (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hammarskjold, Dag (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Han, Ryo Wook (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Harper, Fowler (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hart, Thomas C. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Heckscher, August (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hersey, John (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hickenlooper, Rourke B. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hill, Lister (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hoegh, Leo A. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hoey, Clyde R. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hoffa, James R. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Holden, Reuben (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hook, Sidney (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hoopes, Darlington (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hoover, Herbert (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Howe, Walter (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ickes, Harold I. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Iserman, Theodore (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ives, Irving (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jackson, Colin (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jackson, Robert H. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - James, Edwin L. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Johnston, Eric (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Judd, Walter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kaiser, Philip (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kennan, George (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy, Robert (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy, Thomas (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kerr, Robert S. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kilgore, Harley M. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Killian, James R. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kirchwey, Freda (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kirk, Russell (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Laird, Melvin R. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lamont, Corliss (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lane, Mark (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Laski, Harold (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lawrence, David L. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lee, Richard C. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lehman, Herbert (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lewis, Fulton, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lewis, John L. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Libby, W. F. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lie, Trygve (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Limb, Ben C. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lippman, Walter (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lodge, Henry Cabot (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lodge, John Davis (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Logue, Edward (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Long, Russell B. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lord, Oswald B. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Luce, Henry R. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - MacArthur, Douglas (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McBride, Katherin (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McCarran, Pat (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McCarthy, Joseph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McCloy, John D. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McCormack, John W. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McCormack, Robert (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McGrath, J. Howard (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - McMahon, Brien (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Macomber (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Makarios (Archbishop), Ethnarch of Cyprus (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Malone, George W. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Marcantonio, Vito (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Martin, Joseph W., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Matthews, Herbert (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - May, Catherine (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - May, Edwin (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Meir, Golda (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Merriam, Gordon (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Meyner, Robert (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Middle East (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Millikan, Max F. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mitchell, James P. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Monroney, A. S. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mora, Jose A. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Morgenthau, Henry (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Morris, Robert (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Murray, Philip (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Murrow, Edward R. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Nassar, Gamal Abdel (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Neuberger, Richard (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Nixon, Richard M. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Olds, Irving S. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - O'Neill, J. M. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Oppenheimer, J. Robert (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Palmer, Cecil (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Parkinson, C. Northcote (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Parsons, J. Graham (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Paulding, Linus (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pearson, Drew (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Peck, John Hamilton (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pelly, Thomas M. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pepper, Claude (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Percy, Charles (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pollack, Louis H. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Porter, Charles O. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reed, Paul (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reisel, Victor (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Republican Party (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reston, James (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reuss, Henry S. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reuther, Walter (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Rhodes, John J. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Ribicoff, Abraham (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Rickover, Hyman G. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Robeson, Paul (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanore (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., Jr. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Rostow, Walter (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Saltonstall, Leverett (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sarnoff, Robert W. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Seely-Brown, Horace, Jr. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Smith, Howard W. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Smith, Margaret Chase (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Socialist Workers Party (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Stassen, Harold E. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Stevenson, Adlai (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Stewart, Potter (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Strauss, Lewis (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sukarno (President), Indonesia (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Taber, John (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Taft, Robert A. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Talmadge, Herman E. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Teague, Charles M. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Thomas, Norman (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Thompson, Dorothy (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Thomson, James C. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Tobey, Charles W. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Truman, Harry S. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Turkevich, John (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Uhrie, L. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Velde, Harold H. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Wagner, Robert (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Wallace, Henry (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Wang (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Whiteman, Harold B., Jr. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Records, circa 1935-1987; Accession 1989-A-079
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2022
  - 50th Anniversary, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A History of the Party of the Right, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nathan Hale Award, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kennedy, Edward, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Liberal Party Publications, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1937-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Speakers, 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - On the Left, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Progressive Party, The Progressive Platform, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Rostrum, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Shockley-Innis Debate, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Swan/Griswold Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tory Party Handbook, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Union House, 1937-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Yale Conservative, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Yale Independent and A History of the Yale Political Union and the Independent Party, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Yale Political Journal, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Yale Political Union Leaflets, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Records and memorabilia, 1940-1993; Accession 1995-A-051
  - Constitution, "Guide to Parliamentary Debate," and other internal affairs. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ejection of the Party of the Right, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lists, Memberships and Officers (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lists, Topics and Speakers (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of the Executive Board (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes of the Executive Board, continued (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Party Publications (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publications (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The "Tory Incident", 1989 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Various Posters and Broadsides (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "History of the Tory Independent Party"; interviews with various people, 1977-1978; Accession 1996-A-083
  This accession is closed. Researchers must secure written permission from a current elected or voting member of the Executive Board of the Yale Political Union to access these materials.
  - History of the Tory Party, vol. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interviews
    - Richard Stark Brookhiser, 1978 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Cornford Meyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lawrence Albert Uzzell
      - no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 1977 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1977 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - David Zincavage, undated (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
- Spring Organizational meeting, circa 2000; Accession 2003-A-136
  Item missing since 2012 and is unavailable for research.
- Newsletters and election materials, 1955-1968; Accession 2007-A-217
  - Newsletters and election materials, 1955-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)